PDF_Path,Text,entities
1.pdf,"UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES
United Nations Interim Mission d’Administration
UNMIK
Administration Mission Intérimaire des Nations
in Kosovo Unies au Kosovo
UNMIK
Investigation Task Force
Pristina, 13 December 2004
Case 285/04
time being.
Conclusions
The entire matter has to be seen as an administrative irregularity. It is obvious that international
procurement rules and economic crime law had been breached but the Procurement Regulation
that was in force at that time – Financial Agreement 1999/2 – does not indicate cases like
described before and Kosovo does not have yet any Economic Law.
As agreed with the International Prosecutor, a copy of the Final Report will be provided for him
as background information related to the ITF case no. 286/04.
Recommendations
It is recommended that UNMIK, and in particular, the KTA undertake the following actions:
Recommendation 1: The Airport staff responsible for procurement activity should receive
adequate training in the handling of procurement matters and to adhere to all applicable
Procurement Regulations.
Recommendation 2: The Airport staff responsible for procurement activity has to ensure a fair
competition and pay more attention to check the background of the bidding companies.
2","[('UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES\nUnited Nations Interim Mission d’Administration\n', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo Unies au', 'ORG'), ('13 December 2004', 'DATE'), ('285/04', 'DATE'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Two', 'CARDINAL'), ('at least three', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airport', 'FAC'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor 2 Representative', 'ORG'), ('Vendor 1', 'LAW'), ('51', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Pristina-', 'FAC'), ('Ljubljana', 'GPE'), ('Pristina', 'GPE'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor 2', 'LAW'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('2003', 'DATE'), ('the Fire Station Building. Winner', 'FAC'), ('Vendor 1', 'LAW'), ('third', 'ORDINAL'), ('Vendor 3', 'LAW'), ('Vendor 2', 'LAW'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor 3', 'LAW'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('Euro 19,702 and Euro 21,045.\n', 'LAW'), ('Cramer Antenna.', 'WORK_OF_ART'), ('Vendor 1', 'LAW'), ('Vendor 2', 'LAW'), ('€3,921', 'CARDINAL'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor 3', 'LAW'), ('Vendor 4', 'LAW'), ('€4,278 and', 'DATE'), ('€4,670', 'CARDINAL'), ('31st August and 14th September 2004', 'DATE'), ('Vendor 1', 'LAW'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor 1', 'LAW'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('three Airport', 'DATE'), ('Vendor 3', 'LAW'), ('Vendor 4', 'LAW'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('the Kosovo Organised Crime Bureau\n(', 'ORG'), ('Vendor 4\n', 'LAW'), ('Pristina', 'GPE'), ('Vendor 3', 'LAW'), ('Prizren.\n', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('. 286/04', 'GPE'), ('the\nInternational Prosecutor', 'ORG'), ('October 2004', 'DATE'), ('1 December 2004', 'DATE'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('the International Prosecutor', 'ORG'), ('Economic Law', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('the Procurement Regulation\n', 'LAW'), ('–', 'CARDINAL'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('the International Prosecutor', 'ORG'), ('the Final Report', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('KTA', 'ORG'), (':', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('2:', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airport', 'ORG')]"
10.pdf,"UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES
United Nations Interim Mission d’Administration Intérimaire
Administration Mission in Kosovo des Nations Unies au Kosovo
UNMIK
Investigation Task Force
Irregularities in the procurement for the extension of the
Cargo Apron at Pristina Airport (Case 0282/04)
I. INTRODUCTION
1. This case arises out of an audit report dated 28 February 2003 into the financial
statements of Pristina International Airport conducted by the Chartered
Accountants, which led to an investigation concerning alleged corruption and
irregularities arising in the course of procurements and contracts at Pristina
International Airport.
2. There are four specific allegations in this report of investigation:
• tender specifications produced by the Pristina Airport for the cargo apron
extension were insufficiently specific and without clear instructions for bidder
contrary to UNMIK Finance Regulation 1999/2;
• three persons on the bid opening committee were also part of the technical
evaluation committee contrary to procurement regulations;
Office of the Legal Adviser for clearance; and
• it is alleged that the Vendor was allowed to certify its work as per the
requirements of the contract.
II. APPLICABLE TERRITORIAL LAWS AND UNITED NATIONS
PROCEDURAL RULES
Section 1 of UNMIK Regulation 1999/24 dated 12 December 1999 as amended,
states that the law applicable in Kosovo shall be:
a) “The regulations promulgated by the Special Representative of the
Secretary General (SRSG) and subsidiary instruments issued pursuant to
those regulations; and
b) The Law in force in Kosovo on 22 March 1989.”
UN Staff Regulations 1.2 (b) stipulates, “Staff members shall uphold the highest
standards of efficiency, competence and integrity”
Kosovo Consolidated Budget Funds provides that:
Article 4 1 – “Competition among and participation in the procurement process
shall be maximised.”2
Article 4.1.1 – “All Suppliers and Contractors and their tenders shall be treated
fairly, equally, and non-discriminatorily, without favouritism or prejudice and each
Tender shall be judged on its merits.”
Article 4.3.3. – “If a consultant or any principal, officer or employee of such
consultant has participated or will participate in any manner in the preparation of
the UNMIK Kosovo Interim Administration’s Tendering for a contract, including
but not limited to preparations of specifications or any other Tender Documents,
no such consultant nor any principal officer or employee of such consultant, no
“related person” nor any “illegal payer” may tender for or sponsor or participate in
the Tendering for such contract.”
Article 23.3 – “All tender documents shall contain complete information in neutral
and objective terms so that there can be full and fair competition among all
suppliers. In particular Tender Documents must include the advertisement and ..”
Article 23.3.4 – “…full technical specifications, including the time limits for
delivery and completion.”
Staff Rule 110.1: Misconduct. “Failure by a staff member to comply with his or her
obligations under the Charter of the United Nations, the Staff Regulations and the
Staff Rules or other relevant administrative issuances, or to observe the standards of
conduct expected of an international civil servant, may amount to unsatisfactory
conduct within the meaning of staff regulation 10.2, leading to the institution of
disciplinary measures for misconduct.”
III. METHODOLOGY
Extension.
11. A prequalification evaluation was held 5 April 2001 as a result of which five
companies were pre-qualified to submit bids for the Cargo Apron Extension. Four
companies submitted bids, and following an evaluation, the contract was
awarded to the Vendor. A contract was signed for the Cargo Apron Extension on
11 September 2001.
12. A letter from the Vendor to UNMIK and PEAP dated 9 May 2001 indicates that it
submitted a bid for the Cargo Apron Extension. The tender documents include
what appears to be a section from the preliminary design documents produced by
the Evaluation Company. Specifically, it includes a section entitled ”Bills of
Quantities” from pages 17 and 18 of the Evaluation Company preliminary design
carried out its own soil tests.
25. A letter from the Vendor to PEAP dated 18 September 2003 suggests that the
thereby “self certifying” its own work. Whilst the tender documents at page 5,6
reference 11.4, provide for the Contractor to pay liquidated damages in the event
that the “load-bearing “ capacity of the apron is less than foreseen in the contract,
upon completion of the work, the contract is silent as to whom should carry out
the tests. However, it is questionable as to whether the Vendor should have
carried it out, since it presents a conflict of interest.
instructions on drawings and plans. This appears to have been due to an attempt
to cut costs in preparing the tender documents, as well as a lack of appropriately
qualified staff.
30. In mitigation, the inadequacy of the tender documents also appears to have been
due to ignorance as to the appropriate quantity of detail to be included in the
tender documents rather than a deliberate act calculated to manipulate the tender
process.
conflict of interest.
VII. RECOMMENDATIONS
36. It is recommended that UNMIK ensure that all contracts are referred for legal
advice before signature in order to reduce potential liability issues and avoid a
recurrence of the problems of this instant case. (IV04/282/01)
37. It is recommended that UNMIK ensure that staff understand and comply with the
requirements of the UNMIK Public Procurement Regulation No 2004/3.
(IV04/282/02)
38. It is recommended that UNMIK ensures that all work conducted under contract, in
which the final product has to be evaluated, that said the evaluation be carried
out by a suitably qualified, independent entity. (IV04/282/03)
39. It is recommended that DPKO take appropriate action with respect to DOTI
Official 2 (currently serving with MONUC). (IV04/282/04)","[('UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES\nUnited Nations Interim Mission d’Administration Intérimaire\nAdministration Mission', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('the\nCargo Apron', 'PRODUCT'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('28 February 2003', 'DATE'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Chartered\nAccountants', 'ORG'), ('Pristina\nInternational Airport', 'FAC'), ('four', 'CARDINAL'), (':\n', 'MONEY'), ('the Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('UNITED NATIONS\nPROCEDURAL', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('12 December 1999', 'DATE'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('the Special Representative of the\n', 'ORG'), ('The Law', 'DATE'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('22 March 1989', 'DATE'), ('Public Procurement', 'ORG'), (':', 'CARDINAL'), ('4 1 –', 'DATE'), ('non-', 'ORG'), ('23.3 –', 'CARDINAL'), ('..”\n', 'ORG'), ('23.3.4 – “', 'CARDINAL'), ('the United Nations', 'ORG'), ('the Investigation Task Force. The ITF', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Pillar IV', 'PRODUCT'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'FAC'), ('Yugoslavian', 'NORP'), ('2001', 'DATE'), ('2003', 'DATE'), ('the\nPublic Enterprise Airport Pristina', 'ORG'), ('United Nations Security Council Resolution\n1244', 'ORG'), ('10 June 1999', 'DATE'), ('UNMIK Regulation No 1/1999', 'LAW'), ('25 July 1999', 'DATE'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('Pristina International Airport.\n5', 'FAC'), ('the end of June 2002', 'DATE'), ('the Pristina\nAirport', 'FAC'), ('the Civil Administration Pillar (Pillar II)', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI Official 1 (Department\nof Transport and Infrastructure).', 'ORG'), ('the Transport\nSector of the UNMIK Directorate of Infrastructure Affairs', 'ORG'), ('the end of June 2002', 'DATE'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI', 'ORG'), ('31 July 2000', 'DATE'), ('DOTI Official 1', 'ORG'), ('30 September 2001', 'DATE'), ('United Nations', 'ORG'), ('Airport Engineer 1', 'ORG'), ('the\nConsulting Company.', 'ORG'), ('1 July 2002', 'DATE'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('Pillar II', 'PRODUCT'), ('the Kosovo Trust Agency', 'ORG'), ('Pillar IV', 'PRODUCT'), ('ATCS', 'ORG'), ('1 April 2004', 'DATE'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'EVENT'), ('KFOR', 'ORG'), ('ICAO', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Article 23.4', 'LAW'), ('Public Procurement', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo Consolidated Budget Funds', 'ORG'), ('the Project Engineer', 'ORG'), ('the Evaluation Company', 'ORG'), ('31 January 2001', 'DATE'), ('the Evaluation Company', 'ORG'), ('the Cargo Terminal', 'FAC'), ('Pristina\nAirport', 'FAC'), ('the Cargo Apron\nExtension.', 'PRODUCT'), ('5 April 2001', 'DATE'), ('five', 'CARDINAL'), ('Four', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('11 September 2001', 'DATE'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('9 May 2001', 'DATE'), ('the Evaluation Company.', 'ORG'), ('17', 'CARDINAL'), ('18', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Evaluation Company', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'ORG'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Official 2', 'ORG'), ('18 May\n2001', 'DATE'), ('28 May 2001', 'DATE'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('May 2001.', 'DATE'), ('2b', 'CARDINAL'), ('Cargo Apron', 'PRODUCT'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('2 August\n2001', 'DATE'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('Article 23.3', 'LAW'), ('Public Procurement', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo Consolidated Budget Funds.', 'ORG'), ('Article 23.3', 'LAW'), ('Public Procurement', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo Consolidated Budget\nFunds', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Article 23.3.\n', 'LAW'), ('Cargo Apron', 'PRODUCT'), ('the Evaluation\nCompany', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('the Evaluation Company', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Evaluation Company', 'ORG'), ('CPE', 'ORG'), ('CPE', 'ORG'), ('CPE Procurement Officer', 'ORG'), ('the Procurement Official', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('the CPE Procurement Officer', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Office\nof the Legal', 'ORG'), ('2 August 2001', 'DATE'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('UN', 'ORG'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('24 September 2001', 'DATE'), ('the\nOffice of the Legal', 'ORG'), ('4\n', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('the Cargo Apron', 'PRODUCT'), ('23', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Procurement Official', 'ORG'), ('DOTI Official 1', 'ORG'), ('18 October 2001', 'DATE'), ('DOTI', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('27 June 2001', 'DATE'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('17 October 2001', 'DATE'), ('Airport Engineer 1', 'ORG'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('18 September 2003', 'DATE'), ('5,6', 'CARDINAL'), ('Contractor', 'ORG'), ('Divisional', 'ORG'), ('one', 'CARDINAL'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('Divisional', 'ORG'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('25 August 2002', 'DATE'), ('.\nVI', 'PRODUCT'), ('29', 'CARDINAL'), ('Article 23.4', 'LAW'), ('Public Procurement', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo Consolidated Budget\nFunds', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('CPE', 'ORG'), ('Three', 'CARDINAL'), ('UN', 'ORG'), ('the Office of the Legal', 'ORG'), ('35', 'CARDINAL'), ('Vendor', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('DPKO', 'ORG'), ('DOTI\n', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('MONUC)', 'LAW')]"
105.pdf,"NSA Global SIGINT Highlights
US Intercepts Abe's Secret Plan on Carbon Emissions
WikiLeaks release: July 31, 2015
Keywords: National Security Agency, NSA, Top Secret, SIGINT, NOFORN,
intelligence, intercept, espionage, United States, USA, Japan, Ministry
of Economy Trade and Industry, METI, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, MFA,
Prime Minister, Shinzo Abe, Washington, carbon emissions, Abe
initiative, environment, bilateral relations, climate change
Restraint: SECRET//COMINT//NOFORN
Date: 2007
Organisation: National Security Agency (NSA)
Author: Summary Services Office
Link: https://wikileaks.org/nsa-japan
Pages: 1
the Prime Minister's official residence.Japanese to State Goal of Reducing Carbon Emissions by Half by 2050
result.
Unconventional
Japanese leadership
Z­3/OO/8432­07, 181733Z","[('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('Carbon Emissions', 'PRODUCT'), (': July 31', 'DATE'), ('2015', 'DATE'), ('Top Secret', 'PERSON'), ('SIGINT', 'ORG'), ('United States', 'ORG'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('METI', 'NORP'), ('MFA', 'ORG'), ('Shinzo Abe', 'PERSON'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Half', 'CARDINAL'), ('2050', 'DATE'), ('the Japanese Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Shinzo Abe', 'PERSON'), ('Washington DC', 'GPE'), ('Bush', 'GPE'), ('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('the United States\nof the Prime', 'GPE'), ('Bush', 'GPE'), ('the United States', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Half', 'CARDINAL'), ('2050', 'DATE'), ('26', 'CARDINAL'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Shinzo Abe', 'PERSON'), ('the Japanese Ministry of Economy,\nTrade, and Industry (METI', 'ORG'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('METI', 'PERSON'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), (':', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Ministry of Foreign\nAffairs', 'ORG'), ('MFA', 'ORG'), ('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('half', 'CARDINAL'), ('2050', 'DATE'), ('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('late May', 'DATE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'ORG'), ('Abe', 'PERSON'), ('the United States.', 'GPE'), ('Japanese\xadU.S.', 'LOC'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('181733Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
106.pdf,"NSA Global SIGINT Highlights
US Spies as Japan Doubles Down on Carbon Emissions
WikiLeaks release: July 31, 2015
Keywords: National Security Agency, NSA, Top Secret, SIGINT, NOFORN,
intelligence, intercept, espionage, United States, USA, Japan, European
Energy Agency, IEA, Masakazu Toyoda, carbon emissions,
environment, climate change
Restraint: TOP SECRET//COMINT//NOFORN
Approach
Date: 2008
Organisation: National Security Agency (NSA)
Author: Summary Services Office
Link: https://wikileaks.org/nsa-japan
Pages: 1
officials within the Japanese government. The report observes that Japanese officials remain resolute in
the International Energy Agency (IEA) and the European Union. The report relates speculation by
as is.
Unconventional
Japanese leadership
Z­3/OO/4448­08, 041359Z","[('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Carbon Emissions', 'PRODUCT'), (': July 31', 'DATE'), ('2015', 'DATE'), ('Top Secret', 'PERSON'), ('SIGINT', 'ORG'), ('United States', 'ORG'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('European', 'NORP'), ('Ministry of Economy Trade and Industry,', 'ORG'), ('Masakazu Toyoda', 'PERSON'), (': TOP SECRET//COMINT//NOFORN', 'PERSON'), ('2008', 'DATE'), ('US National Security Agency (NSA)', 'ORG'), ('2008', 'DATE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('the International Energy Agency (IEA)', 'ORG'), ('the European Union.', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('European', 'NORP'), ('Tokyo', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('the\nInternational Energy Agency (IEA)', 'ORG'), ('some European Union', 'ORG'), ('Fatih Birol', 'PERSON'), ('IEA', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('mid\xadMay', 'CARDINAL'), ('Tokyo', 'GPE'), ('Masakazu Toyoda', 'PERSON'), ('the Japanese Ministry of\nEconomy, Trade, and Industry', 'ORG'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), (': first', 'DATE'), ('China', 'GPE'), ('India', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('third', 'ORDINAL'), ('One', 'CARDINAL'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Europeans', 'NORP'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Toyoda', 'ORG'), ('European', 'NORP'), ('ETS', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP')]"
107.pdf,"NSA Global SIGINT Highlights
US Bugged Japan's Confidential G-8 Proposals on
Climate Change
WikiLeaks release: July 31, 2015
Keywords: National Security Agency, NSA, Top Secret, SIGINT, NOFORN,
intelligence, intercept, espionage, United States, USA, Japan, G-8,
Affairs, MFA, Ministry of Finance, Ministry of Environment, Chief Cabinet
Secretary Nobutaka Machimura, carbon emissions, environment,
climate change
Restraint: TOP SECRET//COMINT//REL TO USA, AUS, CAN, GBR, NZL
for G-8 Summit
Date: 2008
Organisation: National Security Agency (NSA)
Author: Summary Services Office
Link: https://wikileaks.org/nsa-japan
Pages: 1
Unconventional
International commercial
3/OO/1447­08, 252149Z","[('Japan', 'GPE'), (': July 31', 'DATE'), ('2015', 'DATE'), ('Top Secret', 'PERSON'), ('SIGINT', 'ORG'), ('United States', 'ORG'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('METI', 'NORP'), ('MFA', 'ORG'), ('Ministry of Finance,', 'ORG'), ('Ministry of Environment', 'ORG'), ('Nobutaka Machimura', 'PERSON'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('AUS', 'GPE'), ('GBR', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('2008', 'DATE'), ('US National Security Agency (NSA)', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('2008', 'DATE'), ('Lake Toya', 'GPE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('the United States', 'GPE'), (': Australia', 'ORG'), ('Canada', 'GPE'), ('Great Britain', 'GPE'), ('New\nZealand', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('AUS', 'GPE'), ('GBR', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('the\nMinistry of Economy Trade and Industry, Ministry of Foreign Affairs', 'ORG'), ('Ministry of Environment', 'ORG'), ('Cabinet', 'ORG'), ('Nobutaka Machimura', 'PERSON'), ('20 February', 'DATE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('the G\xad8 Summit', 'FAC'), ('Lake Toya', 'FAC'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('July.', 'DATE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Summit', 'LOC'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('252149Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
108.pdf,"NSA Global SIGINT Highlights
US Sets NSA on Japan over Cherry Feud
WikiLeaks release: July 31, 2015
Keywords: National Security Agency, NSA, Top Secret, SIGINT, NOFORN,
intelligence, intercept, espionage, United States, USA, Japan, European
Department of Agriculture, food imports, trade liberalization, agriculture,
inspections, beef, cherries
Restraint: TOP SECRET//COMINT//ORCON/NOFORN
Imports
Date: 2009
Organisation: National Security Agency (NSA)
Author: Summary Services Office
Link: https://wikileaks.org/nsa-japan
Pages: 1
Japanese governmental
Z­3/OO/515570­09, 221708Z","[('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Cherry Feud', 'GPE'), (': July 31', 'DATE'), ('2015', 'DATE'), ('Top Secret', 'PERSON'), ('SIGINT', 'ORG'), ('United States', 'ORG'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('European', 'NORP'), ('Ministry of Agriculture Forestry and Fisheries,', 'ORG'), ('MAFF', 'WORK_OF_ART'), ('US', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('2009', 'DATE'), ('2009', 'DATE'), ('the Japanese Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries.', 'ORG'), ('the Ministry for how', 'ORG'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('US', 'GPE'), ('US', 'GPE'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('the Japanese Ministry of Agriculture,\nForestry, and Fisheries (MAFF)', 'ORG'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('U.S.\xadorigin', 'ORG'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('MAFF', 'PERSON'), ('the U.S. Department of Agriculture', 'ORG'), ('Tokyo', 'GPE'), ('the end of this month', 'DATE'), ('MAFF', 'WORK_OF_ART'), ('One', 'CARDINAL'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'ORG'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('221708Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
11.pdf,"UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES
United Nations Interim Mission d’Administration Intérimaire
Administration Mission in Kosovo des Nations Unies au Kosovo
UNMIK
Investigation Task Force
Allegations of theft and corruption arising out of the collection of handling and
landing fees and de-icing costs for passenger aircraft using Pristina Airport.
(Case 0283/04)
I. INTRODUCTION
1. This case arises out of an audit report dated 28 February 2003 into the financial
statements of Pristina International Airport conducted by the Chartered
Accountants which led to an investigation concerning alleged corruption and
irregularities arising in the course of procurements and contracts at Pristina
International Airport.
2. There are three specific allegations in this report of investigation:
• Employees overcharged commercial flights using Pristina Airport for handling and
landing fees and other services.
• Employees failed to account for the money paid to them in handling and landing
fees and other services.
• Employees requested and /or received corrupt payments in return for allocating
landing slots to airlines at the most convenient times.
II. APPLICABLE TERRITORIAL LAWS AND UNITED NATIONS
PROCEDURAL RULES
Section 1 of UNMIK Regulation 1999/24 dated 12 December 1999 as amended,
states that the law applicable in Kosovo shall be:
a) “The regulations promulgated by the Special Representative of the
Secretary General (SRSG) and subsidiary instruments issued pursuant to
those regulations; and
b) The Law in force in Kosovo on 22 March 1989.”
UN Staff Regulations 1.2 (b) stipulates “Staff members shall uphold the highest
standards of efficiency, competence and integrity”
Staff Rule 110.1: Misconduct. “Failure by a staff member to comply with his or her
obligations under the Charter of the United Nations, the Staff Regulations and the
Staff Rules or other relevant administrative issuances, or to observe the standards of
conduct expected of an international civil servant, may amount to unsatisfactory
conduct within the meaning of staff regulation 10.2, leading to the institution of
disciplinary measures for misconduct.”2
III. METHODOLOGY
V. INVESTIGATION DETAILS
10. This case concerns allegations of corruption by staff at Pristina Airport arising
from handling and landing fees levied on passenger aircraft using the Airport in
the period January – December 2001. The case also deals with allegations of
corruption arising from de-icing costs levied on passenger aircraft using the
Airport during the same period and alleged requests for corrupt payments for the
allocation of landing slots to airlines at the most convenient times.
11. Samples were taken from a total of 21 airlines using the airport at Pristina in
2001. The year 2001 was selected due to the fact that fees appear to have been
collected and receipts issued manually. Therefore, it was assessed that a greater
risk of fraudulent activity existed.
12. Where possible, similar dates and the type of aircraft were selected to allow for a
comparative analysis of landing charges and passenger charges.
13. An average price was then calculated for each type of aircraft by selecting a
sample of landings for each airline and multiplied by the number of flights to give
an estimate of the total income from landing fees.
14. The ITF obtained a price list, dated 1 January 2002, which provides an indication
as to the respective costs for basic airport services, based on the weight of the
aircraft.
Handling Fees and De-icing costs
15. The total income from landing fees in 2001 was estimated at DM 14,357,949
(equivalent to €7,341,163. This compares with a figure of €7,376,182 in the profit
and loss accounts produced by the Chartered Accountants.
16. This result suggests that in the absence of further information, the aircraft
charges agreed with the figures produced in the official accounts of the Airport.
However, the integrity of the information on which the accounts are based cannot
be verified. The possibility therefore remains that airlines were routinely
overcharged.
17. It was noted that there are small variations in the prices charged to different
airlines for the same type of aircraft. However, certain airlines appeared to have
measurably lower costs. These were:
• Airline 1 – Average DM 2190
• Airline 2 – Average DM 2888.
18. The receipts books do not indicate whether Airline 1 carried passengers and if so,
how many.
19. It was notable that where aircraft requested de-icing facilities, this appears to
have added considerably to the landing fees costs.
20. A schedule was created detailing costs associated with de-icing. With the
possible exception of one Airline 3 flight, this does not appear to indicate any4
obvious anomalies, although it again did not take into account the possibility that
airlines were uniformly being overcharged for de-icing.
Landing Fees
21. Passenger taxes appear to be charged at 25 DM per passenger. A spreadsheet
was created detailing the total number of persons travelling in the period 1
February 2001 until 31 December 2001 together with the number of persons not
paying passenger tax. The file did not contain any data for the month of January
2001.
22. The spreadsheet produced by the ITF indicated a total of 375,472 passengers
during the relevant period, of whom, 18,996 did not pay the required passenger
tax. If this number is multiplied by 25 DM and converted to Euro per paying
passenger, this gives a total of €4,799,395 as against a stated income figure in
the accounts of €4,919,190 for the whole year. This gap is diminished if a number
of passengers were to be added for the month of January 2001.
23. However, there remains a possibility that the passengers were not being charged
airport tax when they should have been, or that the sums detailed in the accounts
do not equate with sums actually paid.
24. In an effort to verify whether or not airlines were being routinely overcharged for
handling and landing fees or de-icing costs, the ITF sent a request to IATA to
provide information from Airline 3, Airline 4, Airline 5 and Airline 6 concerning any
instances of overcharging or extortion of money by staff at Pristina Airport. The
request also sought information concerning any instances of corruption arising
from the allocation of landing slots at Pristina Airport.
25. Regrettably, to date, no substantive response has been received from the airlines
or IATA.
VI. CONCLUSIONS
26. Whilst the figures for handling and landing fees broadly agree with the figures
produced in the accounts of the Airport, it is not possible to ascertain whether the
source of information forming the basis of the accounts is reliable.
27. In the absence of cooperation from the Airlines and IATA, despite repeated
requests by the ITF, it is not possible to progress the case further.
VII. RECOMMENDATIONS
28. It is therefore recommended that based on the results of this investigation,
UNMIK should prepare an official request to the above-mentioned airlines in an
effort to obtain their support and any information relevant to this matter.
(IV04/283/01)","[('UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES\nUnited Nations Interim Mission d’Administration Intérimaire\nAdministration Mission', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('de-', 'DATE'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('28 February 2003', 'DATE'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Chartered\nAccountants', 'ORG'), ('Pristina\nInternational Airport', 'FAC'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), (':', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('UNITED NATIONS\nPROCEDURAL', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('12 December 1999', 'DATE'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('the Special Representative of the\n', 'ORG'), ('The Law', 'DATE'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('22 March 1989', 'DATE'), (')', 'CARDINAL'), ('the United Nations', 'ORG'), ('.', 'PRODUCT'), ('the Investigation Task Force. The ITF', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Pillar IV', 'PRODUCT'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'FAC'), ('Yugoslavian', 'NORP'), ('2001', 'DATE'), ('2003', 'DATE'), ('the\nPublic Enterprise Airport Pristina', 'ORG'), ('United Nations Security Council Resolution\n1244', 'ORG'), ('10 June 1999', 'DATE'), ('UNMIK Regulation No 1/1999', 'LAW'), ('25 July 1999', 'DATE'), ('UNMIK', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('Pristina International Airport.\n6', 'FAC'), ('the end of June 2002', 'DATE'), ('the Pristina\nAirport', 'FAC'), ('the Civil Administration Pillar (Pillar II)', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Department of Transport\nand Infrastructure (', 'ORG'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('the Transport\nSector of the UNMIK Directorate of Infrastructure Affairs', 'ORG'), ('the end of June 2002', 'DATE'), ('DOTI', 'PERSON'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('DOTI', 'ORG'), ('31 July 2000', 'DATE'), ('DOTI Official 1', 'ORG'), ('30 September 2001', 'DATE'), ('United Nations', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('the\nConsulting Firm.', 'ORG'), ('1 July 2002', 'DATE'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('Pillar II', 'PRODUCT'), ('the Kosovo Trust Agency', 'ORG'), ('Pillar IV', 'PRODUCT'), ('the Airport Sector, KTA', 'FAC'), ('the Air Traffic Control Services', 'ORG'), ('ATCS', 'GPE'), ('1 April 2004', 'DATE'), ('Pristina International Airport', 'EVENT'), ('KFOR', 'ORG'), ('ICAO', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Airport', 'FAC'), ('the period January – December 2001', 'DATE'), ('de-', 'ORG'), ('the\nAirport', 'ORG'), ('21', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina in', 'FAC'), ('The year 2001', 'DATE'), ('.\n13', 'PRODUCT'), ('.\n14', 'PRODUCT'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('1 January 2002', 'DATE'), ('De-', 'PERSON'), ('2001', 'DATE'), ('DM', 'ORG'), ('the Airport.\n', 'ORG'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('one', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airline 3', 'LAW'), ('21', 'CARDINAL'), ('25 DM', 'DATE'), ('the period 1\nFebruary 2001', 'DATE'), ('31 December 2001', 'DATE'), ('the month of January\n2001', 'DATE'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('18,996', 'CARDINAL'), ('25', 'CARDINAL'), ('DM', 'ORG'), ('Euro', 'ORG'), ('the month of January 2001.', 'DATE'), ('de-', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('IATA', 'ORG'), ('Airline 3', 'LAW'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('5', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airline 6', 'LAW'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('IATA.\nVI', 'ORG'), ('Airlines', 'ORG'), ('IATA', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('.\nVII', 'PRODUCT')]"
110.pdf,"(TS//SI//NF) EU, Japan Study Ways to Respond to U.S. Tactics in Doha Round Talks
Unconventional
Japanese leadership
Z-3/OO/33343-06, 291712Z","[('Japan', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('Doha', 'GPE'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('early December', 'DATE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('Brussels', 'GPE'), ('Tokyo', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('Marianne Fischer-Boel', 'PERSON'), ('U.S.', 'ORG'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('17', 'CARDINAL'), ('U.S.', 'ORG'), ('Brussels', 'GPE'), ('last July.', 'DATE'), ('14', 'CARDINAL'), ('15', 'CARDINAL'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Fischer', 'GPE'), ('Boel', 'PERSON'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Fischer-Boel', 'LOC'), ('Klaus-', 'PERSON'), ('Dieter\nBorchardt', 'PERSON'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('8', 'CARDINAL'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('5', 'CARDINAL'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Borchardt', 'PERSON'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('-', 'DATE'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('Cancun', 'GPE'), ('2003)', 'DATE'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('-06', 'DATE'), ('291712Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
111.pdf,"European Leaders Hold Berlusconi Accountable on Italian Financial Situation (TS//SI//NF)
Unconventional
Italian leadership
Z-3/OO/550156-11, 251344Z","[('European', 'NORP'), ('Berlusconi Accountable', 'PERSON'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('22 October', 'DATE'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('Angela Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('French', 'NORP'), ('Nicolas Sarkozy', 'PERSON'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('Silvio Berlusconi', 'PERSON'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('Valentino Valentini', 'PERSON'), ('Rome', 'GPE'), ('. Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('Sarkozy', 'PERSON'), ('Italy', 'GPE'), ('Sarkozy', 'PERSON'), ('Berlusconi', 'PERSON'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('Berlusconi', 'PERSON'), ('the 24th', 'DATE'), ('Valentini', 'PERSON'), ('EU Council\n', 'ORG'), ('Herman Van Rompuy', 'PERSON'), ('Italy', 'GPE'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Van\nRompuy', 'ORG'), ('Spain', 'GPE'), ('Italy', 'GPE'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('11', 'CARDINAL'), ('251344Z', 'DATE')]"
112.pdf,"Italy Would Help Israel Mend Relations With U.S. (TS//SI//OC/REL TO USA, FVEY)
in U.S.-Israeli relations in memory.
SCS, Unconventional
Italian leadership
3/79/37-10, 161635Z; 3/OO/506688-10, 171833Z","[('Italy', 'GPE'), ('Israel', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('USA', 'GPE'), ('Israel', 'GPE'), ('Europe', 'LOC'), ('Italy', 'GPE'), ('the United States', 'GPE'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('13 March', 'DATE'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('Silvio Berlusconi', 'PERSON'), ('Israeli', 'NORP'), ('Binyamin Netanyahu', 'PERSON'), ('--', 'DATE'), ('Israel', 'GPE'), ('1,600', 'CARDINAL'), ('East Jerusalem', 'GPE'), ('Golda Meir', 'PERSON'), ('Netanyahu', 'PERSON'), ('Berlusconi', 'PERSON'), ('Italy', 'GPE'), ('Israel', 'GPE'), ('Washington', 'GPE'), ('Israeli', 'NORP'), ('U.S.-Israeli', 'ORG'), ('Italian', 'NORP'), ('10', 'CARDINAL'), ('161635Z', 'CARDINAL'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('171833Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
113.pdf,"Japan Seeks Long-Term Pact With Specific Figures on Climate Change at G-8 (TS//SI//NF)
(TS//SI//NF) Japan, preparing for its role as chairman of the Group-of-8 (G-8) summit at Lake
Toya early in July, has given notice that it intends to strive for a long-term commitment on
climate change with specific figures, while Germany believes that the crucial issue at the summit
is whether the U.S. will accept going beyond Heiligendamm (the site of last year's G-8 summit)
language in the framework of the G-8 if the emerging countries do not accept numerical targets
at the Major Economies Meeting (MEM). (According to press reports, leaders from 16 countries,
including the members of the G-8 plus China, India, Brazil, Australia, Indonesia, South Korea,
South Africa, and Mexico, plan to discuss climate change on the margins of the G-8 summit in
Japan.) Masaharu Kono, Japan's G-8 sherpa, emphasized Tokyo's position in an exchange with
his German counterpart, Bernd Pfaffenback, on 17 June, while Pfaffenback provided his
country's take on the issues to be addressed at Lake Toya. The German also noted that, in
response to a U.S. request, his country would likely give up its demand for a 25- to 45-percent
mid-term carbon dioxide reduction at the MEM. In addition, he does not believe that the
emerging economies are willing to go beyond the Bali language at present, his feeling being
that they prefer instead to wait until next year's G-8 summit in Copenhagen, because they do
not wish to give up things now that they might be prepared to give up later. It is also
Pfaffenback's position that a failure of the emerging economies to accept a long-term goal with
numbers, even in brackets, would pose difficulties for the G-8 and possibly lead to a clash at the
summit itself if there is no fallback position.
Unconventional
German leadership, Japanese diplomatic
Z-3/OO/4860-08, 191611Z","[('Japan', 'GPE'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('the Group-', 'ORG'), ('G-8', 'GPE'), ('Lake\n', 'FAC'), ('early in July', 'DATE'), ('Germany', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'ORG'), ('Heiligendamm', 'NORP'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('16', 'CARDINAL'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('China', 'GPE'), ('India', 'GPE'), ('Brazil', 'GPE'), ('Australia', 'GPE'), ('Indonesia', 'GPE'), ('South Korea', 'GPE'), ('South Africa', 'GPE'), ('Mexico', 'GPE'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Masaharu', 'NORP'), ('Kono', 'PERSON'), ('Japan', 'GPE'), ('Tokyo', 'GPE'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('Bernd Pfaffenback', 'PERSON'), ('17 June', 'DATE'), ('Pfaffenback', 'ORG'), ('Lake Toya', 'FAC'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('25-', 'CARDINAL'), ('45-', 'DATE'), ('-', 'DATE'), ('MEM', 'ORG'), ('Bali', 'GPE'), ('next year', 'DATE'), ('Copenhagen', 'GPE'), ('Pfaffenback', 'ORG'), ('G-8', 'ORG'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('Japanese', 'NORP'), ('-08', 'DATE'), ('191611Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
114.pdf,"UNSYG Stresses Importance of EU Leadership Role in Climate Change (TS//SI-G//OC/NF)
(TS//SI-G//OC/NF) UNSYG Ban Ki-moon, in an exchange on 10 December with German
Chancellor Angela Merkel, pointed out that the world would be watching the EU with ""keen
interest"" for reassurances that it will maintain its leadership role in combating climate change.
He believes that the mid-December EU Summit in Brussels will impact on the UN Conference
on Climate Change in Poznan as well as the 2009 Copenhagen Talks, stressing that without
positive signals and continued leadership from the EU, it would be difficult for the UN to make a
commitment in Poznan. Ban also maintained that since the new U.S. administration will have a
very engaging and proactive attitude on the issue, the time is right for the EU and the whole
world to create conditions necessary for reaching a meaningful deal at the 2009 UN Climate
Talks. In that regard, Ban considered the Poznan Conference to be very important as a ""bridge""
toward Copenhagen. Ban also praised Merkel for her personal efforts regarding the issue of
combating climate change and for encouraging other EU leaders to agree on the issue. For her
part, Merkel was optimistic that the EU Summit would come to an agreement, although she
acknowledged that the tough issue would involve carbon dioxide trading. Both Ban and Merkel
favored holding a mini-summit in early 2009 to involve the new U.S. administration, believing
that it is important to get a clear idea of U.S. intentions. Merkel believed that the climate-change
issue should be discussed at the heads-of-state level, otherwise it would not work.
Unidentified
UN diplomatic, German leadership
Z-G/OO/503904-08, 112153Z","[('NF)', 'ORG'), ('10 December', 'DATE'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('Angela Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('the mid-December EU Summit', 'DATE'), ('Brussels', 'GPE'), ('the UN Conference\n', 'EVENT'), ('Poznan', 'GPE'), ('2009', 'DATE'), ('Copenhagen Talks', 'EVENT'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('UN', 'ORG'), ('Poznan.', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('2009', 'DATE'), ('UN Climate\nTalks.', 'EVENT'), ('the Poznan Conference', 'ORG'), ('Copenhagen', 'GPE'), ('Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('EU', 'ORG'), ('Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('the EU Summit', 'LAW'), ('Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('early 2009', 'DATE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('U.S.', 'GPE'), ('Merkel', 'PERSON'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('UN', 'ORG'), ('German', 'NORP'), ('-08', 'DATE'), ('112153Z', 'CARDINAL')]"
13.pdf,"UNITED NATIONS UNIES
NATIONS Mission d’Administration
Intérimaire des Nations
United Nations Interim
UNMIK
Unies au Kosovo
Administration Mission
in Kosovo
INVESTIGATION TASK FORCE
Allegations of Bribes/Kickbacks for Employment
at Pristina Airport (Case No. 377/04)
I - Allegations
1. This report summarizes the investigation into a report supplied to the Investigation Task
Force (ITF) alleging that “kickbacks” had been paid to an airport official in order to obtain
employment at Pristina Airport. The allegations were contained in a confidential police
report written by Kosovo Police Service Officer 1 (KPS) serving in the Pristina Airport
Border Police, but originated from Non Staff member 1. The allegations specifically stated
that Non Staff member 1, and others, paid kickbacks to certain high-ranking Pristina Airport
employees in the hope of receiving employment.
II - Background
2. As this case was referred to the Department of Justice on 24 September 2004 and is
currently under two separate judicial investigations, the ITF did not continue with its
administrative investigations. This report summarizes the activities of the ITF. It should
also be noted that dissemination of this report should be severely restricted given the
ongoing criminal inquiries.
III - Investigative Details
3. A separate case - ITF Case No. 2l5/04 - relating to requests for sexual favours in return for
employment had already been under investigation when this report was received. Case No.
215-04 was subsequently closed due to the problem that none of the “victims"" were willing
to come forward and file an official statement on the matter. The reasons given to the ITF for
this fear of making a report was related to the threat of losing already obtained employment
at the airport, or to jeopardize marriages and reputations.
4. Non Staff member 1’s statements provided to the ITF Investigators, disclosed the following
two distinct cases:
Case A
5. On 25-26 July 2004, Non Staff member 1 alleges to have visited Official 1 (Pristina Airport)
asking how he/she could obtain employment at Pristina Airport. He/she stated that Official 1
1had replied that this was possible, but only via the payment of a considerable amount of
money.
6. Non Staff member 1 was aware that two other persons, Non Staff member 2 and Non Staff
member 3 had already paid €7,000.00 each, to Official 1 through the same procedure, in the
hope of receiving employment at Pristina Airport.
7. On either 30 or 31 July 2004, Non Staff member 1 said he/she was contacted by Official 1’s
daughter, Official 2’s Secretary, requesting him/her to come to Restaurant 1 located in
Hajvali.
8. Non Staff member 1 stated that he/she was personally greeted upon his arrival by Security
Official, Official 2’s Secretary and Official 1 and another person, male, but name unknown,
who was there seeking a similar employment route.
9. According to Non Staff member 1, the other person paid, in his presence, the sum of
€10.000,00 to Official 2’s Secretary, just before Non Staff member 1 himself/herself handed
€5.000,00 to the same person.
10. After both persons had paid the agreed upon cash amounts, they were both requested to sign
three different coloured books entitled “Airport Staff”, and then asked to leave because they
would be contacted by telephone as to the details of their future employment at Pristina
Airport.
11. Non Staff member 1 told the ITF that he/she was called again, two days later, in order to pay
an additional € 1.000,00, which he/she had then given to Official 2’s Secretary, in the
presence of his/her father, Official 1, during a dinner that Official 1 and his daughter were
having at the same mentioned restaurant. Non Staff member 1 also said that he/she paid
approximately € 180 for that night’s dinner and that he/she was called, always by Official 2’s
Secretary, to two further dinners at Restaurant 2 and at Restaurant 1. Non-Staff member 1
was requested to pay, amounts of € 225 and € 190 for the dinners. Non Staff member 1 stated
that during the dinner, the following Pristina Airport staff were present: Security Official, a
Secretary, Official 2, X-Ray Official, Official 1, Official 2’s Secretary, Official 3, Official 4
and one person who only spoke English (name unknown). This person may have been
Official 5, because Non Staff member 1 stated that this person was not a Kosovar, but an
International and furthermore, at a certain point when this person was not present, all the
others congratulated Non Staff member 1 for his new job. The Investigators believe that the
above-mentioned Airport staff were attempting to demonstrate to Non Staff member 1 that
they were in contact with the competent person who could authorize his employment.
Case-B
12. Non Staff member 1 stated that he/she was aware of another case of kickbacks for Pristina
Airport employment, which occurred circa 6 September 2004. Non Staff member 1, in his
role as the owner of a hamburger/sandwich stand/restaurant - well-frequented by airport
employees – said he/she was contacted by KPS officer 2 who requested information in
relation to what business connections Non Staff member 4 had within Pristina Airport.
213. Non Staff member 1 stated that Non Staff member 5, the wife of KPS Officer 2 met Non
Staff member 4 in the clothing boutique where he/she worked, while he/she was
purchasing airport uniforms. At that time, he/she had asked him/her how to obtain a job
at the airport. He/she allegedly replied he/she had no problems in getting him/her a job at
Pristina Airport due to his/her important airport contacts, but it would cost him/her €
3.000,00.
V – Conclusion
14. As ITF referred this case to the Department of Justice on 24 September 2004, no further
action was taken by ITF. Therefore, no conclusions can be drawn at this stage on the basis of
ITF Investigations.
V - Recommendations
15. The ITF offers the following recommendations:
Recommendation No. 1: Due to the fact that this case has already been referred to the
International Prosecutor and is currently being investigated by the
Financial Investigation Unit, the ITF recommends that UNMIK
Pillar IV take no administrative action against Airport staff until
the/ judicial process is finalized (IV04/377/01);
Recommendation No. 2: Should the Airport staff not be criminally charged by the
Department of Justice, ITF recommends that UNMIK Pillar IV
should consider appropriate administrative action against
implicated Pristina Airport staff in the light of the Department of
Justice’s findings (IV04/377/02).
3","[('UNITED NATIONS UNIES\nNATIONS Mission d’Administration\nIntérimaire des Nations\nUnited Nations Interim\n', 'ORG'), ('Kosovo', 'GPE'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Investigation Task\nForce (ITF)', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Kosovo Police Service', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('KPS', 'ORG'), ('the Pristina Airport\nBorder Police', 'FAC'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Department of Justice', 'ORG'), ('24 September 2004', 'DATE'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('25-26 July 2004', 'DATE'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('30', 'CARDINAL'), ('31 July 2004', 'DATE'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Restaurant 1', 'ORG'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('three', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina\nAirport', 'FAC'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('two days later', 'DATE'), ('an additional € 1.000,00', 'DATE'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('two', 'CARDINAL'), ('Restaurant 2', 'FAC'), ('Non-', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('€ 225', 'CARDINAL'), ('€ 190', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('3', 'CARDINAL'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('one', 'CARDINAL'), ('English', 'LANGUAGE'), (')', 'DATE'), ('5', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Kosovar', 'NORP'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina\nAirport', 'FAC'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('-', 'CARDINAL'), ('KPS', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('1', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non Staff', 'ORG'), ('5', 'CARDINAL'), ('KPS', 'ORG'), ('2', 'CARDINAL'), ('Non\n', 'ORG'), ('4', 'CARDINAL'), ('.', 'DATE'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Department of Justice', 'ORG'), ('24 September 2004', 'DATE'), ('ITF. Therefore', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), (':', 'CARDINAL'), ('the\nInternational Prosecutor', 'ORG'), ('the\nFinancial Investigation Unit', 'ORG'), ('ITF', 'ORG'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('IV04/377/01);', 'ORG'), ('Airport', 'ORG'), ('the\nDepartment of Justice, ITF', 'ORG'), ('Pristina Airport', 'FAC'), ('the Department of\nJustice', 'ORG'), ('3', 'CARDINAL')]"
14.pdf,"UNITED NATIONS NATIONS UNIES
United Nations Interim Mission d’Administration
Administration Mission Intérimaire des Nations Unies
in Kosovo UNMIK au Kosovo
INVESTIGATION TASK FORCE
Investigation into Allegations of Bribery and Favouritism in Procurement of Uniforms
by Pristina Airport
(ITF Case No. 0462/04)
I. Background and Allegations
1. A Kosovo Trust Agency (KTA) Internal Audit Unit (IAU) Internal Memorandum dated 4
October 2004, which described the audit of the procurement of staff uniforms by Pristina
Airport, raised concerns as to the reasoning for the cancellation of a competitive tender
for summer and winter uniforms (Pristina Airport Reference No. PEAP/CG/UAS/19/05/04)
and the subsequent issue of a single source contract for summer uniforms for new staff
(Pristina Airport Reference No. SHKTA/CG/16-04).
2. In the IAU memo, reference is made to a letter of complaint dated 28-06-04 from Vendor
1, a company that competed for the tender and that was subsequently awarded the single
source contract to supply summer uniforms. The author of the letter, Vendor 1 Manager,
alleged the existence of rumours and witnesses in the matter of the bribery of
Procurement Officer 1, Pristina Airport, and the Finance Officer, Pristina Airport, by one of
Vendor 1 Manager’s competitors in the tender process, Vendor 2. Vendor 1 Manager’s
letter also identified his intention to seek legal action against Procurement Officer 1 for
allegedly violating “the procurement rules” by: replacing a member of the Bid Evaluation
Committee in the competitive tender; allowing a member of the Finance Department, the
Finance Officer, to sit on the committee; and favouring Vendor 2 in the tender process.
3. During the course of the investigation, Procurement Officer 1 told the ITF that, following
the cancellation of the competitive tender, Vendor 1 Manager had made utterances to
him/her that Procurement Officer 1 had interpreted as a threat.
4. The ITF commenced an inquiry into the allegations regarding the procurement process
and now provides a summary of the case and its findings and recommendations.
II. Applicable Law
5. The law applicable to each of the allegations is detailed below.
Allegation 1: that Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer accepted bribes from Vendor
2
Provisional Criminal Code of Kosovo – Article 343 “Accepting Bribes”; Article 344 “Giving
Bribes”
Finance Administration Instruction No. 2/1999 (Revised 15 December 1999) – Public
Conflicts of Interest and Corruption”
Allegation 2: that Procurement Officer 1 replaced a member of the Bid Evaluation Committee
Finance Administration Instruction No. 2/1999 (Revised 15 December 1999) – Public
Competition”; Section 23.9 “Examination and Evaluation of Tenders”
Allegation 3: that Procurement Officer 1 inappropriately included the Finance Officer in the Bid
Evaluation CommitteeFinance Administration Instruction No. 2/1999 (Revised 15 December 1999) – Public
Competition”; Section 23.9 “Examination and Evaluation of Tenders”
Allegation 4: that Procurement Officer 1 favoured Vendor 2 in the tender process
Finance Administration Instruction No. 2/1999 (Revised 15 December 1999) – Public
Competition”
Allegation 5: that Vendor 1 Manager threatened Procurement Officer 1
Provisional Criminal Code of Kosovo – Article 161 “Threat”
III. Investigation Details
6. Procurement Officer 1 managed the competitive tender for the supply of uniforms. In
addition to Vendor 1, Vendor 2 and Vendor 3 submitted bids following which Procurement
Officer 1 convened and chaired a Bid Opening Committee on 10-06-04. Present, in
addition to the committee that comprised members of the various airport work groups,
were representatives of the three bidding companies including Vendor 1 Manager.
7. Procurement Officer 1 also formed and chaired a Bid Evaluation Committee to assess the
offerings of the competitors, which comprised a range of uniforms and accessories for the
various categories of airport employees. On 18-06-04, the committee, though not satisfied
with all Vendor 2’s samples, tentatively decided in favour of that company, the median
bidder in terms of price (Vendor 1 was the highest bidder). The committee resolved that
Vendor 2 would be approached to determine the feasibility of no-cost design changes to
one of the uniforms for women employees. The committee reconvened on 23-06-04 at the
request of Pristina Airport Official. During the meeting, Pristina Airport Official announced
the cancellation of the tender. Pristina Airport Official later awarded a single-source
procurement contract for summer uniforms for newly hired staff, in the amount of
€106,059, to Vendor 1, which had supplied uniforms to the airport under two previous
contracts.
Allegation 1: that Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer accepted bribes from Vendor
2
8. When asked by the ITF to substantiate his/her allegation that Procurement Officer 1 and
the Finance Officer had accepted bribes from Vendor 2, Vendor 1 Manager said that
he/she had heard the rumours in Pristina coffee bars but that he/she could not remember
from whom he/she had heard these rumours. He/she said that the witnesses to whom
he/she had referred in his letter of complaint were actually the same persons from whom
he/she heard the rumours. Vendor 1 Manager was unable to suggest which
representative of Vendor 2 had paid the bribes.
9. Vendor 2 Employee who attended the meeting of the Bid Opening Committee; Vendor 2
Manager; and Vendor 2 Director all told ITF that they had not paid bribes to Procurement
Officer 1 and/or the Finance Officer.
10. Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer both denied accepting bribes or any other
consideration from any person in this matter.
Allegation 2: that Procurement Officer 1 replaced a member of the Bid Evaluation Committee
11. Procurement Officer 1 explained to the ITF that the original nominee to the committee,
Committee member 1, had not been at work on the day that the committee first convened
and, therefore, had been replaced by Committee member 2, who then attended the
second session for continuity purposes. Committee member 1 and Committee member 2
confirmed Procurement Officer 1’s explanation for the replacement.
2Allegation 3: that Procurement Officer 1 inappropriately included the Finance Officer in the Bid
Evaluation Committee
12. The Finance Officer, Procurement Officer 1 and Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that
the Finance Officer participated on the Bid Evaluation Committee. However, Procurement
Officer 1 and Pristina Airport Official each said that the other had nominated the Finance
Officer to the committee. KTA legal staff advised the ITF that the wisdom of allowing a
representative of the Finance Department to participate in bid evaluations is questionable
because, generally, officers whose function involves payment should not evaluate
contractors to whom payment will become due. According to KTA legal staff, however,
such participation is not precluded by any rule or law. Section 23.9.2 of Finance
Administration Instruction No. 2/1999 (Revised 15 December 1999) – Public Procurement
Using Kosovo Consolidated Budget Funds precludes only an “approving officer” from the
Procuring Entity who will eventually sign a contract from serving as a tender evaluator.
The Finance Officer was not an “approving officer” in this procurement process and,
therefore, was not prevented from serving as an evaluator.
Allegation 4: that Procurement Officer 1 favoured Vendor 2 in the tender process
13. In addition to Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer, Bid Evaluation Committee
members Committee member 3, Committee member 4, Committee member 5,
Committee member 6, Committee member 2, and Committee member 7 told the ITF that
the conduct of the committee was completely fair and proper. (Committee member 4 told
the ITF that he/she attended the first session of the Bid Evaluation Committee but that
he/she missed the second session because of the illness of his son.) The general
consensus of the committee was that Vendor 2’s samples were better overall in terms of
quality and design but the committee was not completely satisfied with Vendor 2’s goods.
However, Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that the committee was divided during the
second session, with one group preferring Vendor 2’s goods and the other preferring
those of Vendor 1. Pristina Airport Official said that Procurement Officer 1 (who, as
committee chair, did not have the right to vote) and the Finance Officer argued in favour
of Vendor 2. None of the committee members supported Pristina Airport Official’s
assertions in this regard.
14. The ITF allowed Pristina Airport Official to review a copy of the Bid Evaluation Committee
report prepared by Procurement Officer 1, the last page of which listed the attendees at
the session of the Bid Opening Committee (Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance
Officer were the only members of the Bid Opening Committee who also served on the Bid
Evaluation Committee). Upon looking at the attendee list of the Bid Opening Committee,
Pristina Airport Official named the committee members who, he/she said, had Vendor 1’s
and Vendor 2’s samples respectively. He/she correctly identified Procurement Officer 1
and the Finance Officer but the other four persons whom he/she named were members of
the Bid Opening Committee, not the Bid Evaluation Committee. Pristina Airport Official’s
mistaken identification of these persons as Bid Evaluation Committee members indicates
that his memory of the events of the second committee meeting might be unclear.
15. Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that he/she believed that had he/she not cancelled the
competitive tender, the Bid Evaluation Committee would have awarded the contract to
Vendor 2. Pristina Airport Official said that he/she believed that Procurement Officer 1
had been “primed” to award the contract to Vendor 2 because Procurement Officer 1 had
expressed a preference for and argued in support of Vendor 2’s” inferior product and
because a source (whose identity Pristina Airport Official was unable to recall) had told
him/her that Procurement Officer 1 had been driven to the airport on several occasions by
a person in either the Ministry of Finance or the Ministry of Transportation who was
associated with Vendor 2. Pristina Airport Official said that he/she cancelled the
competitive tender for these reasons. He/she said that he/she did not voice his suspicions
during the committee meeting, adding that he/she did not subsequently report his
suspicions because “priming” is common and if he/she reported every instance he/she
would not have time to do his job. He/she said that proving that Procurement Officer 1
had “pushed” one competitor would have been difficult.
16. Procurement Officer 1 told the ITF that a former Kosovo Minister is his godfather. He/she
said that he/she has never received a ride to the airport from the Former Kosovo Minister
3or in his car. He/she said that he/she has no idea whether the Former Kosovo Minister is
in any way associated with Vendor 2. He/she said that neither the Former Kosovo
Minister nor any other person pressured him/her to show favouritism to Vendor 2.
17. Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that he/she had not seen Vendor 1 Manager’s letter of
complaint and had never heard of Vendor 1 Manager’s allegation regarding the bribery of
Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer. However, Pristina Airport Official’s
administrative assistant said that he/she had been present when Vendor 1 Manager
voiced his suspicion to Pristina Airport Official that an individual from the airport had
accepted bribes. Pristina Airport Official’ administrative assistant said that he/she could
not recall to whom Vendor 1 Manager referred. In addition, he/she told the ITF that
Vendor 1 Manager had given him/her his letter of complaint. Pristina Airport Official’s
administrative assistant said that he/she does not recall whether he/she handed the letter
to Pristina Airport Official or left it for his attention and he/she does not recall Pristina
Airport Official mentioning the letter.
18. Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that, following the cancellation of the competitive
tender, his only alternative to obtain uniforms for newly hired staff was to award a contract
to Vendor 1, who had supplied the airport for the past two years. He/she said that had
he/she let a new tender for summer uniforms, the uniforms would not have been ready
until the end of August (2004).
19. ITF allowed Pristina Airport Official to read a copy of a memo dated 30-06-04 to him/her
from Procurement Officer 1 that described the events of the tender process and
summarized the reasons for its cancellation. Pristina Airport Official told the ITF that,
although he/she had signed the memo, he/she had not “really read” it previously. The
articulated reasons for the cancellation are listed below. Pristina Airport Official and
Procurement Officer 1 said that they had contributed to the list of reasons but disagreed
over which of the reasons had been provided by whom, however, they both said that
Pristina Airport Official had provided the term “unsatisfactory quality”.
i) unsatisfactory quality
ii) unsatisfactory design
iii) evaluation committee not satisfied with the uniforms
iv) no manufacturing details were given
v) documents not completed
20. Procurement Officer 2 told the ITF that he/she transmitted several documents regarding
the single-source procurement of summer uniforms to KTA. Included in the document
package was a Procurement Memo dated 07-07-04 signed by Pristina Airport Official and,
according to Procurement Officer 2, prepared by Pristina Airport Official. (Pristina Airport
Official told the ITF that he/she believes that he/she wrote the justification.) The
justification segment of the memo stated that uniforms would be obtained by single-
source procurement from the current supplier (Vendor 1) for reasons of good quality and
durability.
21. The ITF pointed out to Pristina Airport Official that he/she had referred to the same
uniforms as being of “unsatisfactory quality” and “good quality” in the respective
documents. He/she then admitted “flowering up” his memo and providing embellishment
to ensure that KTA would approve the procurement. He/she said that the term
“unsatisfactory quality” in the memo dated 30-06-04 was poorly chosen and that the
quality of Vendor 1’s uniforms actually met the airport’s requirements. However, he/she
said that the design of the uniforms design was “basic and poor.”
Allegation 5: that Vendor 1 Manager threatened Procurement Officer 1
22. Procurement Officer 1 told the ITF that, on a day (he/she could not specify the date)
following the second meeting of the Bid Evaluation Committee at which the decision was
taken to cancel the competitive tender, Vendor 1 Manager entered Procurement Officer
1’s office and, in the presence of Procurement Officer 2 and a Pristina Airport Civil
Engineer made utterances that Procurement Officer 1 interpreted as a threat. According
to Procurement Officer 1, Vendor 1 Manager said that he/she would meet Procurement
Officer 1 outside; that, because he/she had cancelled the tender, Procurement Officer 1
4would find out who Vendor 1 Manager was; and that Procurement Officer 1 would see
what he/she had done by canceling the tender.
23. Procurement Officer 2 assistant confirmed that he/she had been present during the
incident but he/she had paid only partial attention to what transpired. He/She said that
Vendor 1 Manager might have mentioned that Procurement Officer 1 would have to deal
with KTA Internal Audit and the Investigation Task Force. The Civil Engineer also
confirmed his presence and said that he/she could recall Vendor 1 Manager saying
something to the effect of “You have to see who I am.” The Civil Engineer said that
he/she interpreted the words to mean that Procurement Officer 1 should be afraid of
Vendor 1 Manager.
24. Vendor 1 Manager confirmed that an incident had occurred between him/her and
Procurement Officer 1. Vendor 1 Manager said that he/she told Procurement Officer 1
that he/she was the main reason for the cancellation of the tender and that he/she told
Procurement Officer 1 “You’ll see what you have done. You’ll see that I’ll go to the highest
levels and if necessary, I’ll see you in court.” Vendor 1 Manager said that he/she did not
ask Procurement Officer 1 to go outside with him/her, that he/she did not threaten
Procurement Officer 1 and did not imply that he/she would commit physical aggression.
IV. Findings of Fact
Allegation 1: that Procurement Officer 1 and the Finance Officer accepted bribes from Vendor
2
25. The ITF did not find any evidence to support the allegation that Procurement Officer 1
and/or the Finance Officer accepted bribes from Vendor 2 in this matter. Moreover, the
ITF did not find evidence that any person received a bribe or other compensation or a
promise of a bribe or other compensation in relation to either the competitive tender or the
single-source procurement. Therefore, the allegation of bribery is considered to be
unsubstantiated.
Allegation 2: that Procurement Officer 1 replaced a member of the Bid Evaluation Committee
26. The rationale for replacing the member of the Bid Evaluation Committee is reasonable.
Furthermore, Vendor 1 Manager did not intimate that the replacement was made for any
questionable purpose. Therefore, the allegation is considered to be correct but the
substantive act is not considered to have been based on ulterior motives.
Allegation 3: that Procurement Officer 1 inappropriately placed the Finance Officer on the Bid
Evaluation Committee
27. The ITF established that the Finance Officer participated on the committee but did not
determine whether he/she was nominated by Procurement Officer 1 or Pristina Airport
Official. Regardless, the ITF did not identify any indication that The Finance Officer’s
behaviour on the committee was in any way unprofessional or improper. In the absence
of specific regulations precluding the participation of finance personnel in such processes,
this allegation is considered to be unsubstantiated.
Allegation 4: that Procurement Officer 1 favoured Vendor 2 in the tender process
28. The ITF did not find any evidence to support the allegation that Procurement Officer 1 had
favoured Vendor 2 during the tender process. Similarly, Pristina Airport Official’s opinion
that Procurement Officer 1 had been “primed” to select Vendor 2 is unsubstantiated. The
credibility of Pristina Airport Official’s portrayal of Procurement Officer 1 as a strong
proponent of Vendor 2 in a divided committee was contradicted by the committee
members themselves and undermined by Pristina Airport Official’s misidentification of
most of the members. Procurement Officer 1’s management of the proceedings appears
to have been fair and objective based on the assertions of the members of the Bid
Evaluation Committee. Therefore, this allegation is considered to be unsubstantiated.
Allegation 5: that Vendor 1 Manager threatened Procurement Officer 1
529. The ITF was unable to substantiate that Vendor 1 Manager’s utterances constituted a
threat against Procurement Officer 1.
V. Recommendations
30. The ITF offers the following recommendations:
Recommendation No. 1: It is recommended that UNMIK Pillar IV inform Procurement Officer 1
and the Finance Officer, as well as the KTA Internal Audit Unit, that the ITF did not find any
wrongdoing on the part of Procurement Officer 1 or the Finance Officer. (IV04/462/01)
Recommendation No. 2: It is recommended that UNMIK provide this report to both the
Department of Justice and the Financial Investigation Unit for information purposes, so as to
assist current investigations related to the alleged payment of “kickbacks” in exchange for
employment at Pristina Airport. (IV04/462/02)
